# Paul-Henry Leemann

Researcher in Pure Mathematics

Université de Neuchâtel
Institut de mathématiques
2000 Neuchâtel, Suisse

☑ Paul-Henry.Leemann@unine.ch
 www.leemann.website



## Personal Information

Date of Birth April 12, 1987 Citizenship Switzerland

## Main areas of research

My research interests lie in the intersection of geometric and combinatorial group theory, graph theory and symbolic dynamic. I am particularly interested in groups acting on rooted trees and their (weakly) maximal subgroups, limits and coverings of (Schreier) graphs, rigidity phenomenon in Cayley and Schreier graphs and graphs associated to dynamical systems.

# **Employment**

Since **Université de Neuchâtel**, *Post-Doc*, in Institut de mathématiques, with Alain September 2020 Valette.

2018–2020 **ENS-Lyon**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

Post-Doc Labex MILYON

2016–2018 **ENS-Lyon**, *Post-Doc*, in Unité de Mathématiques Pures et Appliquées, with Mikael de la Salle.

Early Postdoc. Mobility grant supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation

#### Education

2011–2016 **Université de Genève**, *Ph.D. in Mathematics*, "On Subgroups and Schreier Graphs of Finitely Generated Groups", advisor: Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda.

Mention très bien

2013–2015 **Université de Genève**, Basic Certificate of Didactic in Mathematics and in Educational Science.

2009–2011 **Université de Genève**, *M. Sc. in Mathematics*, Master-thesis: "Caractères irréductibles des groupes de Coxeter finis", advisors: Pierre de la Harpe and Tatiana Smirnova-Nagnibeda.

grades: 6/6 (Master-thesis) and 5.7/6 (courses)

2006–2009 Université de Genève, B. Sc. in Mathematics.

Paul-Henry Leemann Curriculum Vitæ

## Publications

1. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms: the case of infinite groups, with M. de la Salle. Accepted in Annales Henri Lebesgue (2020). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.06020

- 2. Finitely generated subgroups of branch groups and subdirect products of just infinite groups, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Izvestia: Math. Vol. 85 (2021) https://doi.org/10.1070/IM9101
- 3. Cayley graphs with few automorphisms, with M. de la Salle. J Algebr Comb (2020). https://doi.org/10.1007/s10801-020-00956-1
- 4. Schreier graphs: Transitivity and Coverings. Internat. J. Algebra Comput., Vol. 26, Issue 1 (2016). www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/S021819671650003X
- 5. Weakly maximal subgroups in regular branch groups, with K. Bou-Rabee and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Algebra, Vol. 455 (2016). www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0021869316001046
- Lamplighter groups, de Bruijn graphs, spider-web graphs and their spectra, with R. Grigorchuk and T. Nagnibeda. Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, Vol. 49, Number 20 (2016). https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1751-8113/49/20/205004

# **Preprints**

- 1. Wreath products of groups acting with bounded orbits, with G. Schneeberger. (2020). https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.08001
- 2. Property FW and wreath products of groups: a simple approach using Schreier graphs, with G. Schneeberger. (2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.03817
- 3. Subgroup induction property for branch groups, with D. Francoeur. (2020). https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.13310
- 4. Up to a double cover, every regular connected graph is isomorphic to a Schreier graph. (2020). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.06431
- 5. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. (2019). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.06399

# Prizes, Grants and Scientific Visits

- 2016 Vacheron Constantin prize for the best thesis in mathematics, Université de Genève
- 07-12 2015 Semester "Analytic and Geometric Aspects of Probability on Graphs", EPFL, Switzer-land
- 01-04 2014 IHP Semester "Marches aléatoires et géométrie asymptotique des groupes", CIRM and IHP, France
- April 2011 Topology and Geometric Group Theory, Columbus, Ohio, USA

# Conferences organisation

- June 2022 "Groups Acting on Fractals" Thematic Trimester, conference organizer, 30 May-3 June, Institut Henri Poincaré, France
- May 2021 Kervaire seminar "Baum-Connes conjecture", co-organizer, 23-28 May, Les Diablerets, Switzerland

2

Paul-Henry Leemann Curriculum Vitæ

Spring 2021 "Group theory, topology and dynamics: Russian-Swiss collaboration", co-organizer, Université de Genève, Switzerland

March 2013 Kervaire seminar "Géométrie des groupes 2013", co-organizer, 10-15 March, Les Diablerets, Switzerland

# Talks (selected)

#### Conferences:

- June 2018 Trees Dynamics and Locally Compact Groups, Heinrich Heine University, Dusseldörf, Germany. Profinite completion of weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups.
- January 2017 Rencontre GAMME, Sète, France. Weakly maximal subgroups of the Grigorchuk group. Existence and construction of IRS.
- November 2014 Paroles aux jeunes chercheurs en géométrie et dynamique, GDR Platon, Université de Bordeaux, France. A criterion for the transitivity of Schreier graphs.
  - June 2014 Workshop in Algebra and Geometry, University of Bern, Switzerland. Transitivity of Schreier graphs and strongly simple groups.
- September 2013 Geometric and Analytic Group Theory, Ventotene, Italy. Transitivity of Schreier graphs.

#### Seminars:

- Februar 2021 Symmetry in Newcastle, University of Newcastle, Australia. Rigidity of Cayley graphs
- December 2020 Séminaire Groupes et Analyse, Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland. Property FW and wreath products, the median graphs point of view
- November 2020 Colloque du département de mathématiques, Université de Neuchâtel, Switzerland. Groups and graphs: rigidity phenomena. Slides (in French): http://www.leemann.website/slides/rigidity.pdf
  - March 2020 Séminaire Groupes et Géométrie, Université de Genève, Switzerland. Weakly maximal subgroups of branch groups. Slides: http://www.leemann.website/slides/weaklymaximal.pdf
  - October 2019 Séminaire de Géométrie, Groupes et Dynamiques, ENS Lyon. Rigidity of Cayley graphs.
    - July 2019 Séminaire Darboux, Montpellier, France. Rigidity of Cayley graphs.
    - May 2015 Ergodic and Geometric Group Theory Seminar, EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland.  $Monstrueuse\ simplicit\'e.$

## Teaching Experiences

## Since 2016 In ENS Lyon:

- Teaching assistant of "Coverings and fundamental groups" (master)
- Teacher of "Introduction to LATEX" (3rd year class)
- 2011–2016 Teaching assistant at the University of Genève:
  - Advanced course on Combinatorics (master)
  - Algebra II: groups, rings, fields, Galois theory (2nd year class)
  - Algebra I: linear algebra (1st year class)
  - Analysis I: basics of logic and set theory, real analysis (1st year class)
  - General mathematics: 1st year class for students of other departments
  - Tutoring for first year students

3/4

Paul-Henry Leemann Curriculum Vitæ

2006–2011 Private tutor in mathematics for high school students

## Refereeing

I have been a referee for the following journals: Journal of Algebra, International Journal of Algebra and Computation, L'enseignement mathématiques, Journal of Algebra and its Applications.

# Scientific popularization

2017 MATHαLYON: interactive workshop in Junior High School, Lyon, France

2014-2016 Mentor in the "boussole" curriculum (one week of immersion in the mathematics' department, for High School's students), Genève, Switzerland

2012-2016 Facilitator at the University "Open Day", Genève, Switzerland

2011-2016 Mathematics' facilitator in Junior High School and High School classes, Genève, Switzerland

2015 Facilitator at the "Science's night", Genève, Switzerland

# Languages

French: native English: fluent German: basics

## Others

Computer skills (LA)TEX (advanced), HTML/CSS and GAP (basics)

Summer camps I have been organizing and running summer camps for children. I have taken part in over thirty camps.

## Recommandation letters

The following people have letters of recommendation available: Rostislav Grigorchuk (Distinguished Professor A&M University Texas, grigorch@math.tamu.edu), Tatiana Nagnibeda (associate professor Geneva Switzerland, Tatiana.Smirnova-Nagnibeda@unige.ch), Mikael de la Salle (assistant professor ENS Lyon France, mikael.de.la.salle@ens-lyon.fr) and Alain Valette (full professor Neuchâtel Switzerland, alain.valette@unine.ch).

4/4